<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>simpleSAMLphp Installation and Configuration</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>2007-08-30</date>

    <pubdate>Mon Oct 15 16:54:59 2007</pubdate>

    <author>
      <firstname>Andreas Åkre</firstname>

      <surname>Solberg</surname>

      <email>andreas.solberg@uninett.no</email>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>The history of simpleSAMLphp</title>

    <para>simpleSAMLphp is an iteration of what was earlier referred to as
    lightbulb (<ulink
    url="https://opensso.dev.java.net/public/extensions/">Sun OpenSSO
    Extensions</ulink>), written by <ulink
    url="http://blogs.sun.com/superpat/">Pat Patterson, Sun</ulink>. There are
    not much code left from lightbulb, but credits go to Pat for introducing a
    new way of thinking when it comes to implementing federation protocols in
    a simple and elegant way.</para>

    <para>The simpleSAMLphp project is currently led by <ulink
    url="http://claimid.com/erlang">Andreas Åkre Solberg</ulink>, <ulink
    url="http://uninett.no">UNINETT</ulink>.</para>

    <para>The product is used to bridge AAI protocols in the GÉANT project,
    <ulink url="http://geant2.net">http://geant2.net</ulink>.</para>

    <para>We have received a bunch of external contributions.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Contributors</title>

      <para>Thank you very much for your contributions to
      simpleSAMLphp:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lukas Hammerle, SWITCH, Switzerland</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Stefan Winter, Restena, Luxemborg</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changelog</title>

    <para>Here is changes between simpleSAML versions. Look here if you are
    upgrading, to see if there are any changes to the config format.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Version 0.5</title>

      <para>Released . Revision X.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Both config.php and metadata format is changed. Look at the
        templates to understand the new format.</para>
      </warning>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Documentation is updated!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Metadata files have been more tidy. Removed unused entries.
          Look at the new templates on how to change your existing
          metadata.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for sending metadata on mail to Feide. Automatically
          detecting if you have configured Feide as the default IdP.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Improved SAML 2.0 Metadata generation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for Shibboleth 1.3 IdP functionality.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added RADIUS authentication backend</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for HTTP-Redirect debugging when enable
          <literal>debug=true</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SAML 2.0 SP example now contains a logout page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added new authentication backend with support for multiple
          LDAP based on which organization the user selects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added SAML 2.0 Discovery Service</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Initial proof of concept implementation of "User consent on
          attribute release"</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed some minor bugs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 0.4</title>

      <para>Released 2007-09-14. Revision X.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Improved documentation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Authentication plugin API. Only LDAP authenticaiton plugin is
          included, but it is now easier to implement your own plugin.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for SAML 2.0 IdP to work with Google Apps for
          Education. Tested.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Initial implementation of SAML 2.0 Single Log-Out
          functionality both for SP and IdP. Seems to work, but not yet
          well-tested.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for bridging SAML 2.0 to SAML 2.0.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added some time skew offset to the NotBefore timestamp on the
          assertion, to allow some time skew between the SP and IdP.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed Browser/POST page to automaticly submit, and have fall
          back functionality for user agents with no javascript
          support.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed some bug with warning traversing Shibboleth 1.3
          Assertions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed tabindex on the login page of the LDAP authentication
          module to allow you to tab from username, to password and then to
          submit.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed bug on autodiscovering hostname in multihost
          environments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Cleaned out some debug messages, and added a debug option in
          the configuration file. This debug option let's you turn on the
          possibility of showing all SAML messages to users in the web
          browser, and manually submit them.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Several minor bugfixes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>News about simpleSAMLphp</title>

    <para>To get the latest news about simpleSAMLphp you can follow this url:
    <ulink
    url="http://rnd.feide.no/category/simplesamlphp/">http://rnd.feide.no/category/simplesamlphp/</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Currently simpleSAMLphp has a project page at Google Code:</para>

    <para><ulink
    url="http://code.google.com/p/simplesamlphp/">http://code.google.com/p/simplesamlphp/</ulink></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Download and install simpleSAMLphp</title>

    <para>You can go to <ulink
    url="http://code.google.com/p/simplesamlphp/">code.google.com/p/simplesamlphp/</ulink>
    to find the most recent release of simpleSAMLphp. Download the zipped
    file, and unzip it on your webserver. However I hightly reccomend running
    from a subversion checkout instead.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting a working copy of simpleSAMLphp from subversion</title>

      <para>Go to the directory where you want to install
      simpleSAMLphp:</para>

      <screen>cd /var</screen>

      <para>Then do a subversion checkout:</para>

      <screen>svn checkout http://simplesamlphp.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/ simplesamlphp</screen>

      <para>If you know subversion you know how to view logs and review
      changes to the files. To update the version you have checked out,
      enter:</para>

      <screen>cd /var/simplesamlphp
svn up</screen>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Making configuration and metadata files</title>

    <para>Configuration and metadata files are stored in a template format,
    you need to copy them to have your local copies. The reason why it is done
    this way, is that when you upgrade you can do svn up in subversion or just
    copy the whole directory over your installation, without replacing your
    existing configuration. When you are updating, you should investigate
    whether the config format is changed, this should be documented in the
    changelog.</para>

    <para>Here are the steps you need to do to create local configuration
    files:</para>

    <screen>cd /var/simplesamlphp
cp config/config-template.php config/config.php
cp -r metadata-templates/*.php metadata/
</screen>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring apache</title>

    <para>In this example simpleSAMLphp is located in
    <filename>/var/simplesamlphp</filename>, that is the default location. If
    you want to modify this location, you can do so freely, but then you need
    to update the path in a few files. <link linkend="sect.altlocations">I
    wrote a separate chapter about that, read on</link>.</para>

    <para>Of the folders inside simplesamlphp, only the www folder needs to be
    accessible from the web. There are several ways of putting the
    simpleSAMLphp depending on the way web sites are structured on your apache
    web server. Here is what I believe is the best configuration.</para>

    <para>Find the apache configuration file for the virtual hosts that you
    want to run simpleSAML on. The configuration may look like this:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;VirtualHost  *&gt;
        ServerName service.example.com
        DocumentRoot /var/www/service.example.com

        Alias /simplesaml /var/simplesamlphp/www
&lt;/VirtualHost&gt;
</programlisting>

    <para>What is special is the <literal>Alias</literal> directive. That
    directive will give control to simpleSAMLphp for all urls that matches
    <literal>http(s)://service.example.com/simplesaml/*</literal>.
    simpleSAMLphp will need to have several SAML interfaces available on the
    web, and all these interfaces are included in the <filename>www</filename>
    subdirectory of your simpleSAMLphp installation. You can set the alias to
    whatever you want, but this alias must be set in the
    <filename>config.php</filename> file of simpleSAML as described in <xref
    linkend="sect.config" />. Here is an example of how this configuration may
    look like in <filename>config.php</filename>:</para>

    <programlisting>$config = array (
[...]
	'baseurlpath'			=&gt; 'simplesaml/',</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The simpleSAMLphp installation webpage</title>

    <para>When you have installed simpleSAMLphp, you can access the homepage
    of your installation, which contains some information and a few links to
    the test services. The url of an installation can be in example:</para>

    <literallayout>https://service.example.com/simplesaml/</literallayout>

    <para>The exact link depends on how you set it up with apache and off
    course your hostname.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>Don't click on any of the links yet, because they require you to
      eigther have setup simpleSAMLphp as an Service Provider or as an
      Identity Provider.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>Here is an example screenshot of what the simpleSAMLphp page looks
    like:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Screenshot of the simpleSAMLphp installation page.</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="resources/simplesamlphp-install/screenshot-installationpage.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Next steps</title>

    <para>You have now successfully installed simpleSAMLphp, and the next
    steps depends on whether you want to setup a service provider, to protect
    a website with authentication or if you want to setup an identity provider
    and connect it to a user storage. We will also provide documentation on
    bridging federation protocols in a separate document.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="simplesamlphp-sp.html">Setting up simpleSAMLphp as a
        service provider</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="simplesamlphp-idp.html">Setting up simpleSAMLphp as
        an identity provider</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="simplesamlphp-bridge.html">Setting up simpleSAMLphp
        as a bridge</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <appendix id="sect.altlocations">
    <title>Installing simpleSAMLphp in alternative locations</title>

    <para>If you want to install simpleSAMLphp in an alternative directory,
    feel free to do so. You need to set the path of the installation directory
    in the config.php file:</para>

    <programlisting>$config = array (
[...]
	'basedir' 				=&gt; '/usr/local/simplesaml/simplesamlphp',</programlisting>

    <para>And you also need to modify the Alias directive in the apache
    configuration:</para>

    <programlisting>        Alias /simplesaml /usr/local/simplesaml/simplesamlphp/www</programlisting>
  </appendix>
</article>