<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>simpleSAMLphp changelog</title>

  <section>
    <title>History</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Change log</title>

    <para>Here is changes between simpleSAMLphp versions. Look here if you are
    upgrading, to see if there are any changes to the config format.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Version 1.0</title>

      <para>Release planned in March 2008.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 0.5</title>

      <para>Released 2007-10-15. Revision 28.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Both <filename>config.php</filename> and metadata format are
        changed. Look at the templates to understand the new format.</para>
      </warning>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Documentation is updated!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Metadata files made tidier. Unused entries removed. Look at
          the new templates on how to change your existing metadata.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Support for sending metadata by mail to Feide. Automatically
          detecting whether you have configured Feide as the default IdP or
          not.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Improved SAML 2.0 Metadata generation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for Shibboleth 1.3 IdP functionality (beta,
          contact me if any problems)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added RADIUS authentication backend</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for HTTP-Redirect debugging when enable
          <literal>debug=true</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SAML 2.0 SP example now contains a logout page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added new authentication backend with support for multiple
          LDAP based on which organization the user selects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added SAML 2.0 Discovery Service</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Initial 'proof of concept' implementation of "User consent on
          attribute release"</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed some minor bugs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Version 0.4</title>

      <para>Released 2007-09-14. Revision X.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Improved documentation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Authentication plugin API. Only LDAP authenticaiton plugin is
          included, but it is now easier to implement your own plugin.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for SAML 2.0 IdP to work with Google Apps for
          Education. Tested.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Initial implementation of SAML 2.0 Single Log Out
          functionality both for SP and IdP. Seems to work, but not yet
          well-tested.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added support for bridging SAML 2.0 to SAML 2.0.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Added some time skew offset to the NotBefore timestamp on the
          assertion, to allow some time skew between the SP and IdP.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed Browser/POST page to automaticly submit, and have fall
          back functionality for user agents with no javascript
          support.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed some bug with warning traversing Shibboleth 1.3
          Assertions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed tabindex on the login page of the LDAP authentication
          module to allow you to tab from username, to password and then to
          submit.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fixed bug on autodiscovering hostname in multihost
          environments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Cleaned out some debug messages, and added a debug option in
          the configuration file. This debug option let's you turn on the
          possibility of showing all SAML messages to users in the web
          browser, and manually submit them.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Several minor bugfixes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>