<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Advanced configuration and maintainance of simpleSAMLphp</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <date>2007-08-30</date>

    <pubdate>Thu Mar 27 20:47:47 2008</pubdate>

    <author>
      <firstname>Andreas Åkre</firstname>

      <surname>Solberg</surname>

      <email>andreas.solberg@uninett.no</email>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <warning>
    <para>This document still in the writing stage.</para>
  </warning>

  <section>
    <title>simpleSAMLphp documentation</title>

    <para>This document is part of the simpleSAMLphp documentation
    suite.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://rnd.feide.no/view/simplesamlphpdocs">List of
        all simpleSAMLphp documentation</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This document assumes that you already have a installation of
    simpleSAMLphp running, configured and working. This is the next step
    :)</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Session management</title>

    <para>simpleSAMLphp has an abstraction layer for session management. That
    means it is possible to choose between different kind of session stores,
    as well as write new session store plugins.</para>

    <para>The <literal>session.handler</literal> configuration option in
    <filename>config.php</filename> allows you to select which session handler
    SimpleSAMLphp should use to store the session information. Currently,
    two session handlers are included in the distribution:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>phpsession</literal> uses the built in session
        management in PHP. This is the default, and is simplest to use. It
        will not work in a load-balanced environement.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><literal>memcache</literal> uses the memcache software to cache
        sessions in memory. Sessions can be distributed and replicated among
        several memcache servers, enabling both load-balancing and
        fail-over.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <programlisting> 'session.handler'       =&gt; 'phpsession',</programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring memcache</title>

      <para>To use the memcache session handler, set the
      <literal>session.handler</literal> parameter in
      <literal>config.php</literal>:</para>

      <programlisting>'session.handler'       =&gt; 'memcache',</programlisting>

      <para>memcache allows you to store multiple redudant copies of sessions
      on different memcache servers.</para>

      <para>The configuration parameter
      <literal>memcache_store.servers</literal> is an array of server groups.
      Every data item will be mirrored in every server group.</para>

      <para>Each server group is an array of servers. The data items will be
      load-balanced between all servers in each server group.</para>

      <para>Each server is an array of parameters for the server. The
      following options are available:</para>

      <glosslist>
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><literal>hostname</literal></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>Host name or ip address of a memcache server runs. This is
            the only required option.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><literal>port</literal></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>Port number of the memcache server. If not set, the
            <literal>memcache.default_port</literal> ini setting is used. This
            is 11211 by default.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><literal>weight</literal></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>Weight of this server in this server group. <ulink
            url="http://php.net/manual/en/function.Memcache-addServer.php">http://php.net/manual/en/function.Memcache-addServer.php</ulink>
            has more information about the weight option.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><literal>timeout</literal></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>Timeout for this server. By default, the timeout is 3
            seconds.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
      </glosslist>

      <para>Here are two examples of configuration of memcache session
      handling:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Example of redudant configuration with load balancing</title>

        <para>Example of redudant configuration with load balancing: This
        configuration makes it possible to lose both servers in the a-group or
        both servers in the b-group without losing any sessions. Note that
        sessions will be lost if one server is lost from both the a-group and
        the b-group.</para>

        <programlisting>'memcache_store.servers' =&gt; array(
  array(
    array('hostname' =&gt; 'mc_a1'),
    array('hostname' =&gt; 'mc_a2'),
  ),
  array(
    array('hostname' =&gt; 'mc_b1'),
    array('hostname' =&gt; 'mc_b2'),
  ),
),</programlisting>
      </example>

      <example>
        <title>Example of simple configuration with only one memcache
        server</title>

        <para>Example of simple configuration with only one memcache server,
        running on the same computer as the web server: Note that all sessions
        will be lost if the memcache server crashes.</para>

        <programlisting>'memcache_store.servers' =&gt; array(
  array(
    array('hostname' =&gt; 'localhost'),
  ),
),</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>The expiration value (<literal>memcache_store.expires</literal>)
      is the duration for which data should be retained in memcache. Data are
      dropped from the memcache servers when this time expires. The time will
      be reset every time the data is written to the memcache servers.</para>

      <para>This value should always be larger than the
      <literal>session.duration</literal> option. Not doing this may result in
      the session being deleted from the memcache servers while it is still in
      use.</para>

      <para>Set this value to 0 if you don't want data to expire.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The oldest data will always be deleted if the memcache server
        runs out of storage space.</para>
      </note>

      <example>
        <title>Example of configuration setting for session expiration</title>

        <para>Here is an example of this configuration parameter:</para>

        <programlisting>'memcache_store.expires' =&gt;  36 * (60*60), // 36 hours.</programlisting>
      </example>

      <section>
        <title>Memcache PHP configuration</title>

        <para>Configure memcahce to not do internal failover. This parameter
        is configured in <filename>php.ini</filename>.</para>

        <programlisting>memcache.allow_failover = Off</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Environmental configuration</title>

        <para>Setup a firewall restricting access to the memcache
        server.</para>

        <para>Because simpleSAMLphp uses a timestamp to check which session is
        most recent in a fail-over setup, it is very important to run
        syncrhonized clocks on all webservers where you run
        simpleSAMLphp.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Load balancing and failover</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Logging and statistics</title>

    <para>simpleSAMLphp supports standard <literal>syslog</literal> logging.
    As an alternative, you may log to flat files.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Apache configuration</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>PHP configuration</title>

    <para>Secure cookies (if you run HTTPS).</para>

    <para>Turn off PHPSESSID in query string.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Getting ready for production</title>

    <para>Here are some checkpoints</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Remove all entities in metadata files that you do not trust. It
        is easy to forget about some of the entities that were used for
        test.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you during testing have been using a certificate that has
        been exposed (notably: the one found in the simpleSAMLphp distribution): 
        Obtain and install a new one.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure you have installed the latest security upgrades for
        your OS.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure to use HTTPS rather than HTTP.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Block access to your servers on anything except port 443.
        simpleSAMLphp only uses plain HTTP(S), so there is no need to open
        ports for SOAP or other communication.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Error handling, error reporting and metadata reporting</title>

    <para>Check out the extras folder for a script that can be embedded in a
    webpage and enable the possibility of sending UI errors to the
    administrators.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-language support</title>

      <para>To add support for a new language, add your new language to the
      <literal>language.available</literal> configuration parameter in
      <filename>config.php</filename>:</para>
  
      <programlisting>  /*
         * Languages available and which language is default
         */
        'language.available' =&gt; array('en', 'no', 'dk', 'es', 'xx'),
        'language.default'   =&gt; 'en',</programlisting>
  
      <para>Please use the standarized two-character <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_ISO_639-1_codes">language codes
      as specified in ISO-639-1</ulink>.</para>
  
      <para>You also can set the default language. You should ensure
      that the default language is complete, as it is used as a fallback when
      a text is not available in the language selected by the user.</para>
  
      <tip>
        <para>This may change in the future. We may distinguish between the
        fallback-lanauge (which is usually English) and the default language.</para>
      </tip>
  
      <para>All strings that can
      be localized are found in the files <filename>dictionaries/</filename>.
      Add a new entry for each string, with your language code, like
      this:</para>
  
      <programlisting>'user_pass_header' =&gt; array(
    'en' =&gt; 'Enter your username and password',
    'no' =&gt; 'Skriv inn brukernavn og passord',
    'xx' =&gt; 'Pooa jujjique jamba',
  ),</programlisting>
  
      <para>You can translate as many of the texts as you would like; a full translation is
      not required unless you want to make this the default language. From the end users
      point of view, it looks best if all text fragments used in a given screen or form
      is in one single language.
      </para>
      
      <para>Note that themes used for customization of the web frontend (see below)
      also may contain language specific texts which you would like to include in your 
      translation. Language independent themes may be created by putting all theme
      texts in a file in the <filename>dictionaries</filename> directory.
      </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Customizing the web frontend with themes</title>

    <para>All XHTML templates are stored in the
    <filename>templates/</filename> directory, one
    subdirectory for each theme. The default theme is named
    <literal>default</literal>. An sample theme is provided, named
    <literal>feidernd</literal>.</para>

    <para>It is possible to define a new theme, where only some of the pages
    are customized. For the rest of the pages, the default theme is used.
    The <literal>feidernd</literal> theme is a good example of this: 
    Only the login page is customized.</para>

    <para>In <filename>config.php</filename> you specify the theme to use, 
    as well as a theme base. The theme base is the fallback
    theme that should be used when the selected theme does not include the
    specific template needed to render a page. Here is an example of a
    configuration:</para>

    <programlisting>    /*
         * Which theme directory should be used? The base is fallback (leave it to default).
         */
        'theme.use'             =&gt; 'feidernd',
        'theme.base'            =&gt; 'default',</programlisting>

    <important>
      <para>The feidernd theme is based on the wordpress login form style.
      Feel free to use this as a base for making your own login form. However:
      Please do not use the feidernd theme unmodified - it contains the
      Feide logo, which of course should be used to identify Feide services, 
      not services provided by your institution.</para>
    </important>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>If you need help to make this work, or want to discuss
    simpleSAMLphp with other users of the software you are fortunate: Around
    simpleSAMLphp there is a great Open source community, and you are welcome
    to join! Both for asking question, answer other questions, request
    improvements or contribute with code or plugins of your own.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://rnd.feide.no/simplesamlphp">simpleSAMLphp
        homepage (at Feide RnD)</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://rnd.feide.no/view/simplesamlphpdocs">List of
        all available simpleSAMLphp documentation</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://rnd.feide.no/content/simplesamlphp-users-mailinglist">Join
        the simpleSAMLphp user's mailing list</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="https://ow.feide.no/simplesamlphp:start">Visit and
        contribute to the simpleSAMLphp wiki</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>